<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The two steps of a nonconformist minister made by him, in order to the obtaining his liberty of preaching in publick : together with an appendix about coming to church in respect to the people / published for a testimony in his generation by a lover of sincerity and peace.</title>
            <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45161</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3714</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32356</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12643415</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12643415</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65066</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45161)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65066)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1528:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The two steps of a nonconformist minister made by him, in order to the obtaining his liberty of preaching in publick : together with an appendix about coming to church in respect to the people / published for a testimony in his generation by a lover of sincerity and peace.</title>
                  <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 34, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"An addition from the author" [signed] John Humfrey -- p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Church and state.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65066:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65066:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TVVO STEPS OF A Nonconformiſt Miniſter; Made by him, in Order to the obtaining his liberty of Preaching in Publick. Together with an APPENDIX about coming to Church in reſpect to the People.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed for a <hi>Teſtimony</hi> in his <hi>Generation,</hi> by a Lover of <hi>Sincerity</hi> and <hi>Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Tim. 5.21.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Doing nothing by Partiality.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Parkhurſt,</hi> at the Three <hi>Crowns</hi> and <hi>Bible,</hi> at the lower end of <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercers-Chappel.</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:65066:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65066:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Firſt Step, BEING My Paper to the Biſhop.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Deſign of this Paper is <hi>Union</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Moderate <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and Sober <hi>Nonconformiſt;</hi> and there is but one Rule muſt be laid down in order thereunto, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing <hi>both</hi> ſenſible that an endeavour after Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord as <hi>Brethren</hi> in the ſame <hi>Reformed Religion,</hi> is an undeniable Duty, and that a wilful neglect of it cannot be anſwered to God by either Party, whoſoever of them ſhall be found in default. The Rule is this, that the <hi>Nonconformiſt</hi> be ready <hi>to do</hi> in the ſincerity of his Conſcience what <hi>he can,</hi> and that out of the like Conſcience to God the Biſhop then does bear with him in what he <hi>cannot,</hi> at leaſt ſo far I hope as the <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Government,</hi> or his
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:65066:3"/>Duty <hi>thereunto,</hi> according to his own private Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of diſcretion, will give way.</p>
            <p>The Nonconformiſt is to conſider well the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance of ſuch Texts as require <hi>Subjection</hi> to the <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> and he is out of Conſcience to the <hi>Fifth Commandment</hi> to comply with their Injunctions to the uttermoſt that may give ſatisfaction, ſo far as he can without ſin. The Biſhop is to conſider the import of ſuch Texts as tell us what a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous thing it is to give occaſion to the doubtful to do anything againſt their Conſciences; and he is out of Conſcience to the <hi>Sixth Commandment</hi> (for fear of <hi>deſtroying him for whom Chriſt died</hi>) to take heed as he would of his life, to put a man upon any more than he is convinced he can ſafely do. When the <hi>Nonconformiſt</hi> now does <hi>what he can,</hi> the Law of God will bear him out in that which he <hi>forbears,</hi> and if he ſuffers, he hath peace in his Soul. If the <hi>Biſhop</hi> likewiſe ſhall receive a man upon this account, as one that cannot require more of him, leſt he <hi>wound</hi> his <hi>weak Conſcience,</hi> and ſo <hi>ſins againſt Chriſt,</hi> I doubt not but the Law of Charity and Mercy, that is, the Law which is <hi>Gods,</hi> will ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie him alſo as to whatſoever he falls ſhort in the fulfilling the Law of <hi>Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is true if the <hi>Biſhop</hi> diſpenſeth, and the <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſt</hi> exceeds, the penalty may be ſued, if there
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:65066:3"/>be any, and any body be ſo affected. It is Law (I ſuppoſe) <hi>in Foro Civili,</hi> and we muſt never <hi>Reſiſt:</hi> but it is no Law <hi>in Foro Dei,</hi> or <hi>Conſcientiae,</hi> for the Authority of thoſe <hi>greater</hi> Laws of <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> does ſuperſede the Execution, ſo that there is no guilt (as to God's ſight I mean) contracted in the omiſſion. God ſays, Thou ſhalt not do any thing which will deſtroy thy Brother, or wound his Conſcience. The Law ſays, Thou ſhalt put him to do thus, and not diſpenſe with him. Whom ſhall the good Biſhop chuſe to obey, the Law of his <hi>God,</hi> or the Statutes of the <hi>Realm?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having therefore thus propoſed the Rule, I will proceed to Practice.</p>
            <p>There are two things (My Lord) neceſſary for me by the <hi>Act</hi> for <hi>Uniformity,</hi> to obtain a liberty of the Pulpit. The <hi>one</hi> is I muſt read before the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop the 39 <hi>Articles</hi> and aſſent to them, and you muſt give me a <hi>Licenſe;</hi> when I have got this, I may be ſent to Gaol if I ſubſcribe not the <hi>Declaration</hi> in the ſaid <hi>Act,</hi> and that is the 2d thing then I muſt do likewiſe. If I do this alſo, your Lordſhip muſt give me a <hi>Certificate</hi> and that with my <hi>Licenſe</hi> will ſerve, ſo that I count then no man <hi>can</hi> and no friend <hi>will</hi> put a bar to my Preaching, where I am peaceably deſired.</p>
            <p>Indeed there is the Declaration of <hi>Aſſent</hi> and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:65066:4"/>
               <hi>conſent</hi> required farther of ſuch as have any prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Church, but if I ſeek nothing but Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to Preach, this cannot be impoſed, becauſe I have no <hi>Place</hi> to make it in, according to the <hi>Act,</hi> and I muſt therefore in all points elſe be dealt with no otherwiſe than a <hi>perfect Conformiſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for my doing theſe two things (ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <hi>my ſelf</hi> willing to do both ſo far as <hi>I can,</hi> and your Lordſhip willing to condeſcend to me in what <hi>I cannot,</hi>) I do apprehend that in reading the <hi>Articles,</hi> I may take leave as I go along to make my explication of any Article, and if my ſenſe be ſuch as is agreeable to your Lordſhips Judgment, or at leaſt what you judg fit to be allowed, you may paſs me as to the <hi>Articles;</hi> and if you will then afford me the like liberty of Explication in <hi>Subſcribing</hi> the <hi>Declaration</hi> alſo, I have no more to do but to ſet down my explications of the <hi>one</hi> and the <hi>other,</hi> and leave both to your Lordſhips <hi>candour</hi> and <hi>conſcience</hi> to <hi>receive</hi> me or <hi>reject</hi> me, as it ſhall pleaſe <hi>God</hi> and your <hi>Lordſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I begin with the Articles.</p>
            <p>The Thirty nine Articles of the Church I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive as Articles for <hi>Concord,</hi> (according to the Title) and not as Articles of <hi>Faith,</hi> and I ſuppoſe my ſelf therefore not tyed up to the <hi>Authentick</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:65066:4"/>ſenſe of the <hi>Impoſer</hi> (as I think we are in <hi>Laws</hi>) but to be allowed the liberty of a <hi>Doctoral</hi> Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation; That is, whereas in a Convocation every Doctor there (or Member thereof) is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed or granted, in paſſing ſuch Articles or Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons to abound in his own ſenſe, ſo long as he can but reconcile the words to it. Let a man make any rational conſtruction of an Article which is agreeable either to the <hi>preciſe words</hi> (for that he may well think to be the mind of ſome or other of the <hi>Doctors,</hi>) or to the <hi>ſenſe</hi> which he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves to be the <hi>meaning</hi> of the <hi>major part,</hi> though varying from the words (for that, above any, when it can, is to be embrac'd) it is ſufficient (<hi>I</hi> count) in point of Conſcience, for his Aſſent to the ſame. Neither do <hi>I</hi> by an Aſſent to a thing according to my preſent Judgment, ſhut up my underſtanding from receiving and owning any <hi>far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> or <hi>other</hi> Truth, whereof <hi>I</hi> ſhall be convinced hereafter. This liberty being foreprized, <hi>I</hi> do declare my unfeigned <hi>Aſſent</hi> to the ſaid <hi>Articles,</hi> with theſe <hi>Explications</hi> or <hi>Cautions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">As Chriſt died for us, and was buried: ſo alſo' is it to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, that he went down into Hell.</note>
               <hi>Art.</hi> 3. <hi>I</hi> aſſent to the <hi>words,</hi> they are <hi>Scripture,</hi> and my <hi>Creed,</hi> but I am uncertain of the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:65066:5"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Chriſt did truly riſe again from death, and took again his body, with fleſh, bones, and all things appertaining to the perfection of mans Nature, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he aſcended into Heaven, and there ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, until he return to judge all men at the laſt day.</note>
               <hi>Art.</hi> 4. That Chriſt aroſe and aſcended with his proper <hi>fleſh and bones,</hi> it is certain, yet whether upon his entring into the heavenly glory (as <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi>) this <hi>fleſh and bones</hi> of his were not transformed into a <hi>ſpiritual body, I</hi> do queſtion, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Apoſtle tells us expreſly, That <hi>fleſh and blood cannot inherit the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> We may refer this <hi>fleſh and bones</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to his <hi>Riſing</hi> and <hi>Aſcenſion,</hi> but leave it <hi>in dubio</hi> in regard to his <hi>Sitting in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">In the name of the Holy Scripture, we do underſtand thoſe Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Books of the Old and new Teſtament, of whoſe Authoríty was never any doubt in the Church.</note>
               <hi>Art.</hi> 6. By <hi>[Church]</hi> I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the whole <hi>Catholick</hi> Church, or this <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> for it is evident that there hath been doubt made of ſome Books in our Canon by Antient <hi>Particular</hi> Churches and <hi>Fathers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Three Creeds, <hi>Nice</hi> Creed, <hi>Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi>'s Creed, and that which is commonly called the Apoſtles Creed, ought thorowly to be received and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved: for they may be proved by moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Warrants of Holy Scripture.</note>
               <hi>Art.</hi> 8. The word <hi>[tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly]</hi> I underſtand only in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the <hi>Articles</hi> of thoſe <hi>Creeds,</hi> not in regard to the <hi>Proem</hi> and <hi>Concluſion</hi> of the <hi>Athanaſian Quicunque vult,</hi> which is inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:65066:5"/>
               <hi>I</hi> hold with the Goodneſs of God, and Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The condition of man after the Fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> is ſuch, that he cannot turn and prepare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by his own natural ſtrength and good works to Faith, and calling upon God: Wherefore we have no power to do good works pleaſant and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Grace of God by Chriſt preventing us, that we may have a good will, and working with us when we have that good will.</note>
               <hi>Art.</hi> 10. By the words <hi>[no power]</hi> and <hi>[cannot]</hi> I underſtand a <hi>Moral</hi> power and impotency, which lyes in ſuch a diſpoſition, as that a man never <hi>will,</hi> without the ſpecial grace of God: but not ſo, as if we had no power at all that is <hi>Phyſical;</hi> or as if the terms of the <hi>Covenant of Grace</hi> were <hi>Impoſsible</hi> to any.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">We are accounted righteous before God only for the merit of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt by Faith, and not for our own works or deſervings: Wherefore that we are juſtified by Faith only, is a moſt wholſom Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and very full of comfort, as more large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is expreſſed in the Homily of Juſtification.</note>
               <hi>Art.</hi> 11. By the words <hi>[Faith only]</hi> I underſtand what <hi>Paul</hi> means by <hi>[Faith without works]</hi> that is, Faith in oppoſition to works, that would make the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to be of <hi>debt,</hi> and not of <hi>grace,</hi> or to <hi>works of the Law,</hi> works which the Law requires to Juſtification (which none have, and if any be juſtified at all, it muſt be therefore <hi>without them,</hi> not in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to Repentance, and Evangelical Obedience: and though it be for <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s ſake, or <hi>his</hi> merits, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:65066:6"/>not <hi>ours,</hi> that he accounts us <hi>righteous,</hi> yet is our Faith, Repentance, and ſincere Obedience, the condition upon which he does it; or rather the Righteouſneſs it ſelf, which upon the account of Chriſt's deſerving, he accepts unto life everlaſting.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Works done before the grace of Chriſt, and the inſpiration of his Spirit, are not pleaſant to God, foraſmuch as they ſpring not of Faith in Jeſus Chriſt, neither do they make men meet to receive grace, (or as the School-Authors ſay) deſerve grace of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruity: yea, rather for that they are not done as God hath willed and commanded them to be done, we doubt not but they have the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ſin.</note>
               <hi>Art.</hi> 13. When <hi>good works done before grace</hi> are ſaid to have <hi>the nature of ſin,</hi> I underſtand that thô ſuch works are good <hi>quoad operis ſubſtantiam,</hi> yet they are evil <hi>quoad modum quo ordinantur ad vitam aeternam,</hi> and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when they are ſaid <hi>not to be pleaſant unto God,</hi> I underſtand, not acceptable unto Salvation. <hi>I</hi> judg that the doing what we can through the ſtrength of <hi>free will,</hi> and <hi>common</hi> grace, is not to be diſcouraged, and to be held in ſome good ſenſe preparatory to ſaving Converſion; yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is no <hi>full promiſe</hi> made thereunto as the condition of obtaining that grace which is <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial,</hi> it is truly ſaid, that ſuch works do not <hi>make us meet</hi> for receiving, or do not <hi>of congruity de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve</hi> the ſame.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:65066:6"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Predeſtination to life is the everlaſting purpoſe of God, whereby (before the foundations of the world were laid) he hath conſtantly decreed by his Counſel, ſecret to us, to deliver from curſe and damnation thoſe whom he hath choſen in Chriſt out of mankind, and to bring them by Chriſt to ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Salvation, as Veſſels made to honour. After we have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Holy Ghoſt, we may depart from grace given, and fall into ſin; and by the grace of God (we may) ariſe again, and amend our lives.</note>
               <hi>Art.</hi> 16, 17. I apprehend the Church here does follow St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in the Points of <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> and <hi>Perſeverance;</hi> and when it is ſaid, that, <hi>after we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Holy Ghoſt, we may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from grace given,</hi> it muſt be underſtood ſo, as that the Elect for all that, ſhall never <hi>finally fall away,</hi> but ſhall infallibly <hi>reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> and be ſaved.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">They are to be had accurſed, that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to ſay that every man ſhall be ſaved by the Law or Sect which he profeſſeth, ſo that he be diligent to frame his life according to that Law, and the light of nature. For holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth ſet out unto us only the name of Jeſus Chriſt whereby men muſt be ſaved.</note>
               <hi>Art.</hi> 18. I obſerve the Church hath but one <hi>Anathema</hi> in all her Articles, and that ſeems to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced here againſt all thoſe who do, or ſhall hold that any perſons can be ſaved that are not Chriſtians, as if the <hi>Death of Chriſt,</hi> or benefits thereof, and the <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of him</hi> were commenſurate through the world. But God forbid! I am out of doubt that God hath a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment over all mankind, which is Moral in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to Life and Salvation, and that the inſtrument
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:65066:7"/>of that Government muſt be the Law of <hi>Grace</hi> (the Law of <hi>Innocency</hi> becoming in the ſtate of <hi>Lapſed Nature,</hi> uncapable of that end) which being at firſt promulgated to <hi>Adam</hi> after his Fall, and to <hi>Noah,</hi> muſt belong to all their Poſterity, inſomuch as every one (whoſoever he be) that lives up in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity to this Law, according to that adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it he is under, ſhall be ſaved. For my Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent then to this Article, I do deſire the word <hi>[by]</hi> may be eſpecially noted. I could not aſſent to this Article, if it were <hi>[in the Law or Sect he profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth,]</hi> but being <hi>[by,]</hi> I hold plainly, that if a Heathen, or any Perſon that never heard the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, repents of his ſin, and truſts to a good God, and lives up to the <hi>Law</hi> (or Covenant) <hi>of Grace ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the firſt Edition of it,</hi> (I ſay, if any ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed do, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.26. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.35.) and thereby comes to be ſaved, it is by the Chriſtian Religion which he <hi>implicitely</hi> holds in the ſubſtance with us, and not <hi>[by the Law &amp; Sect that he profeſſeth]</hi> that he is ſaved. And this Salvation of his is in and through the Name and Mediation of Jeſus Chriſt, no leſs than ours is, who procured that Law for them and all the <hi>World,</hi> as well as for <hi>Abraham</hi> and the Jews under the <hi>Old,</hi> and for us under the <hi>New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:65066:7"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Church hath power to decree Rites or Ceremonies, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in controverſies of Faith.</note>
               <hi>Art.</hi> 20. The <hi>Church</hi> I think hath <hi>[Power to Decree Rites or Ceremonies,]</hi> that is, ſome Rites, not any whatſoever, provided ſhe uſes due caution, not placing matter of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip or Neceſſity, much leſs Merit or Juſtification in them, nor ſcandalizing her Members thereby, and not impoſing them, when they need not, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of her Communion: Yet if ſhe does ſo, and the <hi>Impoſition</hi> be unlawful, if thoſe Rites or Ceremonies be not ſinful in themſelves, we cannot (I apprehend) refuſe our <hi>ſubmiſſion</hi> for all that, ſo long as the <hi>Supream Power</hi> confirms the ſame. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain the Church <hi>hath authority in controverſies of Faith,</hi> not to make any <hi>new Articles</hi> thereof, for that were <hi>Antichriſtian:</hi> but upon mature debate to judge what points are <hi>de fide</hi> (or neceſſary accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Scripture to be received) and what not: Only this authority when ſhe hath done, is Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial, or <hi>Declarative,</hi> not <hi>Conſtitutive</hi> of duty, as <hi>Chriſt's</hi> the Lawgiver's is, and as <hi>Princes,</hi> or the Supream Magiſtrates in his Sphear is ſo alſo. <hi>The Clergy in their Convocation is to order and ſettle them, having firſt obtained leave under our broad Seal ſo to do, and we approving their ſaid Ordinances,</hi> ſays the King in his Declaration before theſe Articles.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:65066:8"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Whoſoever through his private judgment, willingly and purpoſely doth openly break the Traditions and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the Church, which be not repugnant to the Word of God, and be ordained and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by common authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ought to be rebuked openly, (that others may fear to do the like) as he that offendeth againſt the common order of the Church, and hurteth the authority of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, and woundeth the conſciences of the weak brethren.</note>
               <hi>Art.</hi> 34. I aſſent to this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle as parallel with the laſt mentioned, and I gain-ſay not, but the open breakers of the Churches <hi>Traditions</hi> or <hi>Ceremonies</hi> may be <hi>reproved</hi> for the ſake of others: Yet in regard that ſome of theſe Traditions or Ceremonies may be <hi>repugnant to the Word of God</hi> in the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>ſome</hi> men, which are not to <hi>others,</hi> I apprehend both that the reaſons of ſuch ought to be heard, and that we cannot condemn any for acting ſo among others, as to have always a care never to do any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Conſcience for Company.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond Book of Homilies, the ſeveral ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles whereof we have joyned under this Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, doth contain a godly and wholſome Doctrine, and neceſſary for theſe times, as doth the former book of Homilies, which were ſet forth in the time of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth: and therefore we judge them to be read in Churches by the Miniſters diligently, and diſtinctly, that they may be underſtanded of the people.</note>
               <hi>Art.</hi> 35. I receive this <hi>Article</hi> on an <hi>implicite</hi> faith, and I deſire that may ſerve, becauſe I have not read over the <hi>Homilies,</hi> and cannot aſſent any otherwiſe therefore, till I have.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:65066:8"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The book of Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration of Archbiſhops and Biſhops, and orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Prieſts and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, lately ſet forth in the time of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth, and confirmed at the ſame time by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Parliament, doth contain all things neceſſary to ſuch Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration and Ordering: neither hath it any thing that of it ſelf is ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious and ungodly.</note>
               <hi>Art.</hi> 36. <hi>I</hi> underſtand by <hi>Superſtition</hi> and <hi>Ungodlineſs,</hi> two perticular <hi>Species</hi> of that which is <hi>ſinful. I</hi> dare not ſay that there is nothing at all in the whole Book of Conſecration and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders here mentioned, that is ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful: The Article does not ſay ſo, but that there is not <hi>any thing in it that of it ſelf is Superſtitious or Ungodly,</hi> that is, ſinful upon the account of either of theſe particular ſpecies of ſin. And to this I think <hi>I</hi> may aſſent, at leaſt after <hi>I</hi> have added this caution, that theſe Articles were agreed upon in the year 1562. and new publiſhed by King <hi>James,</hi> and that this book therefore muſt be underſtood of the <hi>old</hi> book in his time, and not of the book as it is of <hi>late altered</hi> with the <hi>new Preface</hi> put to it, wherein there is one thing eſpecially (which I paſs here nameleſs) too too hard for my Approbation.</p>
            <p>Having thus given my <hi>Explication,</hi> with what I <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed</hi> before it, it is fit I make yet ſome little farther <hi>apology</hi> for this liberty. There is a threefold <hi>Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> according to <hi>Suarez</hi> in his excellent Book <hi>De Legibus:</hi> An <hi>Authentick, Uſual, and Doctoral</hi> (I think he calls it <hi>Doctrinal</hi>) interpretation. I have explai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:65066:9"/>
               <hi>two</hi> of the terms in the beginning, and the <hi>third</hi> needs no explanation, and <hi>I</hi> need not <hi>it.</hi> Theſe <hi>Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> of the <hi>Church I</hi> ſuppoſe to be ſubſcribed general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with this preſumption that we may uſe a <hi>Docto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> Interpretation; but the queſtion indeed may be whether a man can ſtrictly in point of Conſcience give his aſſent, or ſubſcribe to any <hi>Article,</hi> unleſs he believe it to be true in the <hi>Authentick</hi> ſenſe, or meaning of the <hi>Impoſers, I</hi> muſt confeſs <hi>I</hi> have had ſuch an impreſſion on my mind, that unleſs <hi>I</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve an <hi>Article</hi> in that ſenſe, which <hi>I</hi> take to be the ſenſe of the <hi>majority</hi> of the <hi>Convocation</hi> that paſſed the <hi>Articles,</hi> I could not chooſe but ſcruple the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring my aſſent to it for fear of a <hi>Lye;</hi> and yet do I find that an <hi>Uſher</hi> and <hi>Hammond,</hi> the <hi>Arminians</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts</hi> do ſubſcribe the ſame <hi>Articles</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out making any ſcruple about their diverſity of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation. <hi>I</hi> find alſo that in the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Trent</hi> the Doctors differ'd in moſt points, yet as ſoon as they were but contrived into ſuch words as might ſalve the contrary opinions, they paſſed them as unanimous in the <hi>Council,</hi> writing after one againſt another, and citing the <hi>Council</hi> for them on both ſides. There is this difference therefore ſeems reaſonable to be made between a <hi>Law</hi> and a <hi>Doctrinal Theſis</hi> for <hi>eſtabliſhing conſent in the matter of Religion;</hi> That when the <hi>one</hi> muſt be taken ſtill in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:65066:9"/>the <hi>Authentick,</hi> the <hi>other</hi> is to be conſtrued in a <hi>Doctoral</hi> interpretation. <hi>I</hi> have intimated it before, <hi>I</hi> muſt now give my reaſon, which is alſo ſaid, but not applied. It is becauſe the authority of a <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver</hi> is <hi>Magiſterial</hi> or <hi>Imperative,</hi> that conſtitutes duty, and his will is uncontroulable: but the <hi>Paſtors</hi> authority, or Convent of <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Preſbyters,</hi> for agreement in points of Doctrine, is <hi>Miniſterial</hi> and <hi>Declarative</hi> only (<hi>I</hi> may uſe the ſame terms <hi>I</hi> hope <hi>I</hi> have before, and nauſeate no body) obliging not, <hi>niſi ſententia non errante,</hi> or no farther than they be agreeable to <hi>Gods Word;</hi> and while every one does judge of <hi>that,</hi> there muſt be a diverſity of interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, it being not equal that ſo many <hi>Articles</hi> ſhould be ſubſcribed by all, but upon that ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition. <hi>I</hi> never could be ſatisfied therefore with that <hi>coming off</hi> which is propoſed by ſome great and ingenious men (ſuch as <hi>Chillingworth</hi>) as ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for ſubſcribing theſe Articles, that they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand nothing elſe by it, but an obligation not to preach or write againſt them. A gloſs both <hi>too laxe,</hi> becauſe they do not ſubſcribe, <hi>I engage ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to write or preach againſt the Articles,</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs their unfeigned <hi>aſſent</hi> to them, and if this be underſtood of the <hi>Authentick</hi> ſenſe, they cannot profeſs it: and <hi>too ſtreight,</hi> becauſe, when they preach upon any ſuch point, they will ſpeak (do
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:65066:10"/>what they can) according to their own Opinion, and ſo break their Engagement. It were to be wiſhed therefore, that if ever we have a <hi>Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> that Sits to do any thing, they would paſs ſome ſuch New <hi>Canon</hi> (moſt fit to be decreed) as may declare that the <hi>Articles</hi> and <hi>Homilies</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> are not required to be ſubſcribed, but with this freedom of a <hi>Doctoral interpretation.</hi> Were ſuch a liberty authorized by an <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> or <hi>Convocation,</hi> the conſcience were put out of doubt: In the mean while when others are ſatisfied with the reaſonableneſs of the thing, whether it be <hi>authorized</hi> or not, I finding my ſelf in doubt about it, am forced to this courſe, which is to ſecure my peace by my aforeſaid <hi>Explication,</hi> and my fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized declaration concerning the matter.</p>
            <p>I proceed now to the <hi>Subſcription,</hi> or <hi>Declaration</hi> required to be <hi>ſubſcribed</hi> by the <hi>Act.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Underſtanding by <hi>taking Arms,</hi> raiſing War, or joyning in it, and by the King, his Sacred Perſon and Authority, I ſubſcribe the firſt clauſe thereof, <hi>That it is n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> lawful to take Arms againſt the King upon any pretence whatſoever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Underſtanding the word <hi>abhor,</hi> in a cool ſenſe [I diſclaim,] and by the <hi>Commiſſionated</hi> thoſe who <hi>have,</hi> and <hi>purſue</hi> their <hi>Commiſſions</hi> according to <hi>Law,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:65066:10"/>I ſubſcribe the Second Clauſe of it; <hi>And that I do abhor that Traiterous Poſition of taking Arms by his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> (or by Law, that is, upon <hi>pretence</hi> of it, for the Poſition elſe is impoſſible) <hi>againſt his Perſon, or againſt thoſe that are Commiſsionated by him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Third Clauſe <hi>I</hi> take to be an Indefinite Promiſe of uſing Common Prayer, which in the main <hi>I</hi> am not againſt: And I do therefore ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, that if <hi>I</hi> have a Publick Charge or Cure of Souls, <hi>I</hi> ſhall in the <hi>ordinary conſtant Lords Day Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,</hi> ordinarily, by my ſelf, or by my Aſſiſtant, according to the uſage of the Church, <hi>Rebus ſic ſtantibus,</hi> Conform <hi>to the Liturgy of the Church of</hi> England <hi>as it is now by Law eſtabliſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether this be the ſenſe of the Law-giver al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together, it may be a doubt: but in this ſenſe, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing it to be ſo, or with theſe limitations there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, if it be otherwiſe, I ſet my name.</p>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:65066:11"/>
               <head>The Second Step, BEING A leſſer Requeſt, the former not obtained.</head>
               <p>IT was the <hi>policy</hi> of the Contrivers of the <hi>Act for Uniformity,</hi> that thoſe <hi>Miniſters</hi> who were engaged in the late times on the <hi>Parliament</hi> ſide by <hi>taking the Covenant,</hi> ſhould renounce it, or be debarred the liberty of their Miniſtry for <hi>twenty years,</hi> accounting I ſuppoſe that if any ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pervived <hi>that time,</hi> there could be no danger in their <hi>re-admiſſion.</hi> There was a clauſe therefore in the <hi>Subſcription</hi> beſides thoſe before going, which <hi>concern'd the Covenant,</hi> and was the foreſt part of this <hi>injunction,</hi> abiding in force till the <hi>laſt year,</hi> and then it <hi>expired.</hi> It was believed that many of the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> upon the expiration would have flocked in, and ſubſcribed, but <hi>I</hi> know not of <hi>any who took the Covenant,</hi> but my <hi>ſelf</hi> only <hi>who took it not,</hi> that have made any <hi>tryal</hi> upon that occaſion. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs to proceed in what I have begun, having
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:65066:11"/>Wrote this Paper, and preſented it to the Biſhop the laſt year (1682) when that clauſe ceaſed, I think good this year (1683) to Print it, upon the account enſuing.</p>
               <p>I do apprehend there is a kind of univerſal guilt upon the <hi>Conformiſt</hi> (ſome few alwaies ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) in receiving our late <hi>Impoſitions</hi> hand over head, as they did, which they ſhould rather have all refuſed as one man, and required explanation. How many were there prepared (the good God vouchſafe us all a ſight of our ſins, and forgive them) to declare their <hi>aſſent</hi> and <hi>conſent</hi> to <hi>all</hi> and <hi>every</hi> thing in a <hi>book</hi> before they ſaw it, at leaſt read it with any examination as they ſhould have done? How many more were there yet more forward to <hi>ſubſcribe</hi> a <hi>Declaration,</hi> wherein there were ſo many hard things to be ſwallowed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any had wrote about them, or themſelves able to digeſt ſcarce any one branch of it? It was their intereſt to comply, but how they could <hi>declare</hi> and <hi>ſubſcribe</hi> ſo ſoon (or perhaps can yet) in <hi>Truth, Judgment</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> the Lord knows.</p>
               <p>On the other ſide, I am no leſs ſenſible of a great deal of <hi>weakneſs</hi> and <hi>prejudice</hi> among our brethren, in judging things <hi>ſinful</hi> that are <hi>not,</hi> and conſequently <hi>Superſtition</hi> in placing fear and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in ſuch things. There is beſides, no little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitedneſs
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:65066:12"/>of ſome mens being <hi>more holy</hi> than the <hi>Conformist,</hi> and conſequently <hi>Pride, Uncharitableneſs, Judging of others;</hi> and if any Perſons ſhall <hi>ſeparate</hi> from the <hi>publick</hi> on ſinful grounds, it is really <hi>Schiſm,</hi> and in real Schiſm how many evils are there in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded?</p>
               <p>In this caſe of <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Scandal,</hi> which we ſee on both ſides, I would fain know what way there is for any of us to eſcape, but by following the rule I have laid down.</p>
               <p>On the point of <hi>Sin. If I aſſent</hi> to the <hi>Articles,</hi> and <hi>ſubſcribe</hi> the <hi>Declaration</hi> without an <hi>Explication,</hi> then do I aſſent to what I think <hi>true,</hi> and what I think <hi>not true</hi> in thoſe Articles, and I <hi>ſubſcribe</hi> that which <hi>I</hi> take to be the <hi>good ſenſe,</hi> and that which is alſo the <hi>bad ſenſe</hi> of the Declaration, which ſeems <hi>unlawful</hi> to be done, as what neither becomes a <hi>good Chriſtian,</hi> or <hi>true Engliſh-man:</hi> But if I aſſent and ſubſcribe with an <hi>Explication,</hi> then do I <hi>aſſent</hi> only to what I judg <hi>true</hi> in thoſe <hi>Articles,</hi> and I <hi>ſubſcribe</hi> only the <hi>good ſenſe</hi> of the <hi>Declaration,</hi> which ſeems not only what is <hi>lawful,</hi> but <hi>fit</hi> to be done, both as a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and <hi>good Subject,</hi> who is to be Loyal to the Government of the Nation.</p>
               <p>On the point of <hi>Scandal.</hi> If I ſhall aſſent and ſubſcribe as others, without any Caution, Limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or Explication, then ſhall <hi>I (quantum ad me)</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:65066:12"/>harden the <hi>Conformiſt</hi> (who hath Conformed blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) in his ſin and impenitence, and draw the <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſt</hi> (who judgeth it unlawful) to do that which is againſt his Conſcience by my Example. If I do nothing, or <hi>not</hi> endeavour what <hi>I can,</hi> I nurſe up my <hi>Brethren</hi> in thoſe Evils before-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, and give occaſion to the <hi>Conformiſt</hi> to ſay, Theſe men can do thus and thus, more than they do; and ſeeing they are ſuch peeviſh, obſtinate perſons, we do well to ſubmit to all that is En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned our ſelves, and perſecute them, and ſo do I become a <hi>ſtumbling-block</hi> to the <hi>one,</hi> and to the <hi>other:</hi> But if I <hi>aſſent</hi> and <hi>ſubſcribe</hi> with <hi>Explication,</hi> (that is, do as <hi>much,</hi> and <hi>only</hi> what <hi>I can</hi>) then do I <hi>deliver my own Soul,</hi> neither partaking with my <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi> in theſe Evils out of which I ſtrive to bring them by my Example, nor give occaſion to the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſt</hi> of any hardning, who ſeeing in me a regard to Authority, together with a care of my Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in my <hi>Explications,</hi> he may come to be <hi>judged in his own Thoughts;</hi> and being ready perhaps then to hearken to any ingenuous Admonition, ſo long as it is tendred in ſuch a way as is not affected, or done with preference of my Underſtanding or Piety above his, but with Humility, and ſenſe of my own failings, at leaſt in many other things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he ſo much excels me, he may be brought (the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:65066:13"/>good Spirit of God graciouſly aſſiſting) to that <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance</hi> which is meet <hi>towards God,</hi> and that <hi>Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation towards us,</hi> which we ſeek with him.</p>
               <p>And now if my <hi>Dioceſan,</hi> or <hi>Metropolitan</hi> (which I would chuſe rather) or any other <hi>Biſhop</hi> (they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing) will vouchſafe me only this condeſcenſion in ſubſcribing the Declaration, to ſpeak to their <hi>Regiſter,</hi> that in ſetting my name to his Book, <hi>I</hi> may have leave to do it in theſe words, <hi>According to a Paper delivered in by me to the Biſhop I ſubſcribe, I</hi> ſee no reaſon but <hi>I</hi> may put my name to his <hi>Book,</hi> as well as to this <hi>Paper;</hi> and any other may do ſo too, giving in the ſame, or ſo much of it (for all our <hi>Nonconformists</hi> have not their Exceptions alike) as himſelf needs.</p>
               <p>I would urge the Argument of <hi>Naamans</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants. If the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> required <hi>ſome great thing</hi> of the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> for us to come in and unite with them (eſpecially under our common danger) <hi>would not</hi> they <hi>do it?</hi> and will they refuſe us ſo ſmall a matter? If none of them for all that will be got to grant us this, then muſt I commit the Cauſe of the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> to Almighty <hi>God,</hi> to be <hi>Judg</hi> therein between <hi>them</hi> and <hi>us</hi> in this matter.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:65066:13"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Appendix, BEING</hi> My Judgment about coming to Church, and the Caſe of Private Meetings.</head>
            <p>BEfore <hi>I</hi> leave my Province, <hi>I</hi> think fit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect a little on what <hi>I</hi> have ſaid, in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to my Brethren of the Nonconform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Party, who will be apt, many of them, to be offended at me, that <hi>I,</hi> who am one of them, ſhould be ſo indifferent to either ſide, as I appear, which if it be a fault, I confeſs it; I am guilty of that impartiality or writing without reſpect of perſons, which I cannot help; and if that fault will make the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Party bear with me more equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly than my <hi>Brethren,</hi> I think they deſerve to be blamed.</p>
            <p>Indeed I hope that as for the moſt part of the Diſſenters, it is out of the <hi>true Fear of God</hi> that they chuſe the way wherein they go; but though I think that Fear of God to be <hi>true,</hi> I think it not <hi>pure</hi> and <hi>unmixt</hi> without <hi>Errour,</hi> and without <hi>Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:65066:14"/>They think (I will ſuppoſe, for I mean not as to all of them) the going to <hi>Church</hi> unlawful, and therefore ſet up <hi>Meetings:</hi> As they do this then, becauſe they are afraid to ſin, it is the Fear of God; but as there is Errour in this Fear, doubting of that to be ſin which is none, this Fear turns to Superſtition, and Superſtition can be no good ground for any thing a man does. The evil they fear being no evil, the cauſe for what they do is <hi>no cauſe,</hi> and to ſeparate from the <hi>Church without a cauſe,</hi> I hold to be <hi>Schiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For my own part I am perſuaded in my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience that it is lawful to go to a <hi>Meeting,</hi> and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to go to <hi>Church,</hi> and I am ſorry we have ſuch a company of ſuperſtitious folks of both ſides; Men and Women of the <hi>Conformiſts</hi> that think it a ſin to go to a <hi>Meeting,</hi> and of the <hi>Nonconformiſt</hi> that thinks he ſins if he go to <hi>Church,</hi> when there is no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Chriſtians whatſoever, where the Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials of Chriſtianity are, but to ſeparate from them without a cauſe, whether on one ſide or other, is Schiſm. I ſay not that every <hi>Conformiſt</hi> therefore that goes to <hi>Church,</hi> and never to a <hi>Meeting,</hi> does in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur this guilt, becauſe, though he be <hi>locally</hi> never at a <hi>Meeting,</hi> yet does he not <hi>mentally</hi> ſeparate from the <hi>Meeters,</hi> who holds them for all that to be true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and counts it no ſin to joyn with them in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:65066:14"/>Communion, if he h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d reaſon: Only he is himſelf well ſatisfied with the Service of the <hi>Church,</hi> and he hath no reaſon for his going otherwhere. It is not ſo on the part of the <hi>Nonconformiſt;</hi> there is a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Magiſtrate, that he ſhall come to Church, &amp; if he does not, he muſt have ſome more prevailing reaſon or cauſe that will juſtifie his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing it, or elſe his Separation being <hi>cauſleſs</hi> (I muſt ſtill ſay) cannot but be ſin, and conſequently Schiſm. If this pleaſe ſome, it may be I ſhall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe them in what I ſay next; and if it diſpleaſe ſome, I may next pleaſe them; but I ſpeak my Conſcience. A Perſon is ſet apart for the Office of the Miniſtry; he being not able to conform, is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited to Preach in Publick; having a Call in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, he Preaches in a <hi>Meeting;</hi> what is there in this, which the Apoſtles own caſe does not juſtifie? <hi>Whether it be meet to obey God or man, judge ye.</hi> I think moreover, that the Commiſſion of Chriſt which warrants a <hi>Miniſters</hi> Preaching, does alſo warrant the <hi>Hearers;</hi> becauſe <hi>Preaching</hi> and <hi>Hearing</hi> are <hi>Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> which will mutually draw one another. <hi>I</hi> muſt add, if ſome good men farther, out of a ſenſe of wrong to the Ejected, do think themſelves bound to come ſometimes and hear ſuch Miniſters for ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging their Miniſtry, and delivering their Souls from participation of the guilt of thoſe that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:65066:15"/>Ejected them (eſpecially if they were heretofore their own Paſtors) <hi>I</hi> take this to be ſo much more Chriſtian, and juſtifiable before God. But if theſe <hi>Miniſters</hi> and <hi>People</hi> do judg the Pariſh-Church no <hi>true Church,</hi> or that it is a <hi>ſin</hi> to go thither (not having any Exception which is <hi>particular,</hi> but what reaches all <hi>Parochial Congregations</hi>) and upon that ground ſet up their <hi>Meetings, I</hi> do not ſee (this ground of theirs being a miſtaken ground, or this cauſe for their <hi>Separation</hi> being ſuch as will not hold, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently <hi>no cauſe</hi>) how they can be juſtified from the aforeſaid Imputation.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Miniſter</hi> to Preach (<hi>I</hi> muſt inculcate) up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account of <hi>Chriſts Commiſsion,</hi> preferring his <hi>Maſters</hi> Authority before <hi>Mans,</hi> that is, upon the plea of <hi>greater duty,</hi> and for the <hi>People</hi> to come to hear by virtue of the ſame <hi>Commiſsion,</hi> upon the ſame plea ſtill of <hi>farther</hi> (or greater) <hi>Edification</hi> (as men go ordinarily to hear other Miniſters than their own) not in a way of <hi>Separation</hi> from the Publick Miniſters or Pariſh-Churches, but in <hi>Conjunction</hi> with them (ſpeaking ſtill ſo far as concerns God's word) I do maintain lawful: But if any of my Brethren do offer another Plea that muſt draw with it a ſeparation from the Pariſh Church, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be that of holding ſuch Churches to be no <hi>true Churches,</hi> or that the <hi>Church</hi> does impoſe ſuch
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:65066:15"/>things as conditions of her <hi>Ordinary, Conſtant Lay-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> which are <hi>ſinful</hi> or intolerable, As I am of Opinion, that they can make no ſuch plea good; ſo muſt I heartily adviſe them to take heed, becauſe if they do ſtand upon ſuch a one, their Separation being without cauſe, if the Pariſh-Churches be true Churches, and it be no ſin to go to them, they know the Charge lyes againſt them. I will add, To ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from any Church, upon a reaſon common to others, as becauſe we have a <hi>Liturgy,</hi> or the like, is virtually to ſeparate from all that have one, and conſequently from the moſt of Churches in all Ages of the World.</p>
            <p>The truth is, there is ſuch an impreſſion got on the imaginations of ſome of the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> that if they ſhould come in to the Church ſo as to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> and ſubmit to her preſent <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions;</hi> nay, if they ſhall but touch with the <hi>Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt</hi> almoſt in any thing, though only to <hi>go to Church</hi> with them, and take the <hi>Sacrament</hi> there (which yet as to Lay-conformity is in effect indeed all) they are afraid, as if it were the receiving upon them the <hi>Mark of the Beaſt</hi> (I mean, the doing ſome very horrid thing they know not well elſe what) and were therefore to be caſt remedileſs into the <hi>Lake of Fire.</hi> A buſineſs really of very ſad conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to our ſelves at home, as exceeding ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:65066:16"/>to the <hi>Reformed Churches</hi> abroad, who have their <hi>Liturgies</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> as we have, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſome or other of them leſs innocent than this of the <hi>Church of England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I will ask here, What think we of <hi>Bradford, Philpot, Latimer, Ridley, Cranmer,</hi> and the reſt that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in Q. <hi>Mary</hi>'s time? Were there not amongſt theſe holy Martyrs an <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> and <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and did not they go ordinarily to <hi>Church,</hi> and receive the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament according to the <hi>Liturgy</hi> as we do, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of all the Impoſitions beſides in King <hi>Edward</hi>'s days? Nay, what think we of the old <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> in Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s and K. <hi>James</hi> his time, who, though they laid down their Miniſtry rather than to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to ſome Impoſitions afterwards, did yet main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Communion with the Pariſh-Churches all their days? Did any of theſe now, or all theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the <hi>Mark in their right hands,</hi> or in their <hi>fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads</hi> by this means? And muſt they therefore be everlaſtingly damned?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> argue: The receiving the Mark in the <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> muſt be a ſin certainly, becauſe the receiver is caſt into Hell for it. But to obey the Law, or to conform only ſo far as we can (which is the Rule of theſe Papers) is the duty of every man, &amp; no ſin.</p>
            <p>Again; if receiving theſe Impoſitions be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Mark, it muſt be the promiſcuous recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:65066:16"/>them, without caution, (which to beware of is the end of theſe Papers) or againſt Conſcience, that is, ſinfully receiving them: But to receive them (as I here propoſe) with <hi>Explication</hi> (which is to receive them no otherwiſe but ſo as they may and ought to be received) is to get a <hi>victory over the Mark,</hi> avoiding the ſin in the doing.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs I am ſorry that I have need to ſay thus much, I wiſh I had not; but there are ſome odd minds, ſome vehement Revelation-men, ſome melancholy Spirits, and I am much aſſured that ſuch a conception I ſpeak of is not uncommon to ſuch. As for thoſe that never had any ſuch kind of thought, but have their rational Exceptions, it will yet be well even for them, when they ſhall be able to get off their proper Objections, ſo as to come honeſtly to Church, with a Judgment that is ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and not only to avoid the Law, to be ſecured from this alſo after they have done; who can tell what impreſſion the ſuggeſtions of a mans own heart, if troubled, or the words of another upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion may lay upon him? And as for ſuch as are for diſputing the Point, if they can produce thoſe Arguments as will prove that the <hi>Church</hi> hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed impoſed any thing as the condition of her <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary</hi> Communion, which is ſinful and intolerable, &amp; thoſe Arguments be ſound, then muſt I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:65066:17"/>the Schiſm which is made by their Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from her Communion through thoſe ſinful Impoſitions, muſt be imputed to her, &amp; the <hi>Church of England</hi> is the <hi>Schiſmatick</hi> till ſhe removes them: But if thoſe Arguments be not ſufficient or unſound, then muſt the Schiſm which is made, be imputed to them. For if the cauſe upon which they ſeparate be found no cauſe (and an inſufficient one is none) <hi>I</hi> muſt aſſert ſtill, that the Separation here con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived being <hi>cauſleſs,</hi> muſt be Schiſm.</p>
            <p>But what if it <hi>be</hi> Schiſm? There are many ſuch Miniſters, and ſuch People, who are rivetted in the belief, that the Pariſh-Churches are no true Churches, or at leaſt, that it is ſin to go thither, and what ſhall theſe do? I anſwer, I need not ſtand to ſay firſt what all will, that theſe men are to lay down their Errour, and ſo come to Church, as the only way to eſcape ſin; but ſeeing they can never be convinced of that, I muſt ſay, there are degrees of Sin and Schiſm, and the greateſt evil muſt be moſt carefully ſhun'd. To ſet up Meetings upon the account theſe do, is ſin, is Schiſm, I take it: but to hold no Meetings at all, and leave off the Aſſembling themſelves together, ſo as to rob God of his Worſhip altogether, this is certainly more ſinful, more wicked, more intolerable. It appears conſequently in the iſſue, that a Toleration (under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:65066:17"/>ſuch a one as is meet, or of ſuch as are Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable) is even almoſt as neceſſary to be granted by His Majeſty and a Parliament, when we have one, as a conſtant and continued Pardon from God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty is to this poor divided Nation.</p>
            <p>Not that I deny but there may be <hi>Reaſons</hi> for the Meetings of <hi>Diſſenters</hi> (and perhaps very <hi>many</hi>) that will hold, and cannot be gainſaid; and when <hi>I</hi> ſay that ſeparating from the Church upon ſuch grounds as draw ill conſequences after it, and will not hold, is <hi>Schiſm,</hi> I do not ſay that every meer local Separation from the Pariſh-Meeting when there is cauſe, is <hi>ſo,</hi> who am ſenſible what a <hi>Scare-crow</hi> hath been made of that bare word only, as Mr. <hi>Hales</hi> hath obſerved. Suppoſe a man ſtands upon his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty from <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Nature,</hi> to chuſe his own <hi>Paſtor</hi> for the benefit of his Soul, as his own <hi>Phyſician</hi> for the health of his Body, and ſo uſing thoſe means which he finds moſt conducive to his own edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he ſits down with ſuch or ſuch a <hi>Meeting</hi> for his <hi>ſtated</hi> Communion, when yet he refuſes not to go to <hi>Church,</hi> maintaining <hi>occaſional</hi> Communion alſo with his <hi>Pariſh, I</hi> will not deny but ſuch a man hath reaſon. Indeed, if he quite leave the <hi>Church,</hi> I ſhall ſuſpect, according to my Principles, that his ground is not good, and that is all one as that he hath <hi>none.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You will ſay, if I go to <hi>Church,</hi> I muſt own the <hi>Pariſh,</hi> and I muſt own the <hi>Dioceſs,</hi> and I muſt own
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:65066:18"/>the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and his <hi>Government.</hi> I anſwer, and ſo you may; but it is not neceſſary that you own them as of <hi>Divine Right,</hi> which others I ſuppoſe do. Upon that <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> I muſt confeſs I do not ſee how any Separation from the <hi>Church</hi> (unleſs in caſe of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing impoſed that is <hi>ſinful</hi>) could be juſtifiable, and the <hi>Conformiſts</hi> therefore taking up that Principle, do generally condemn <hi>all Meetings,</hi> accuſing them without diſcrimination of <hi>Schiſm:</hi> But it is <hi>one</hi> thing to own the Pariſh-Church, the Dioceſs, the Biſhop, &amp; Epiſcopal Government <hi>according to Law,</hi> and <hi>another</hi> to won them as of <hi>Divine Inſtitution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I apprehend that <hi>Particular Congregations,</hi> where there is a <hi>Paſtor</hi> and <hi>Flock</hi> conjoyned for the Worſhip of God, &amp; carrying on an holy life, are the Churches of <hi>Chriſts appointment,</hi> and that every Miniſter of ſuch a particular People hath a power of <hi>Governing</hi> them, as well as <hi>Teaching</hi> them, derived to him from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> being <hi>Epiſcopus Gregis,</hi> by virtue of his <hi>Office,</hi> &amp; if any then ſhall go to ſet up an <hi>Epiſcopus Poſtorum,</hi> a Biſhop of the Dioceſs to diveſt him that is Paſtor of a particular Congregation (or the Miniſter of the Pariſh) of that Authority which Chriſt hath committed to him for governing his Flock (which he that makes a <hi>Dioceſs</hi> to be the only Church of <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> Inſtitution, and the <hi>Dioceſan</hi> the <hi>ſole Paſtor,</hi> muſt do) let him conſider what he undertakes, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the burden which is hereby laid on the <hi>Biſhop,</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:65066:18"/>and the account he muſt make at the great day for the Souls of ſo many he takes no particular care at all of, is intolerable.</p>
            <p>I will own the <hi>Biſhop</hi> and his <hi>Regiment,</hi> but not to the denial of the <hi>Miniſters.</hi> I will own a <hi>Dioceſs,</hi> but not to the unchurching <hi>Particular Congregations.</hi> There is another conſideration therefore to be had of the <hi>Church</hi> than this here underſtood, and that is, as it is <hi>National,</hi> and the King the Head of it. The Church as <hi>National</hi> is divided into two <hi>Provinces,</hi> and theſe into twenty ſix <hi>Dioceſſes,</hi> and they into ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſand <hi>Pariſhes.</hi> The Pariſh-Church conſiſts of a Particular Congregation, which is therefore a Church of <hi>Chriſts appointment,</hi> and the Authority or Regiment the Miniſter, Paſtor, or Biſhop of ſuch a Flock hath, is derived from <hi>Chriſt.</hi> The Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty the <hi>Dioceſan</hi> hath is derived from the <hi>King.</hi> The King makes the Biſhops (he might make them if he pleaſed, as <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth by <hi>Commiſsion</hi>) and he is the Fountain of their Honour, for they have <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronies,</hi> and upon that account ſit in the <hi>Lords Houſe;</hi> and if we may look on them accordingly as his <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers,</hi> to exerciſe no other Authority as <hi>Dioceſans,</hi> but what they derive from him, then, As the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and of the <hi>Paſtors</hi> are of a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent kind, (the Power or Regiment of the <hi>Paſtor</hi> being <hi>internal,</hi> or <hi>in ſacris,</hi> and <hi>formally</hi> Eccleſiaſtical, flowing immediately from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but the Regiment
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:65066:19"/>of the <hi>Biſhop external,</hi> or <hi>circa ſacra,</hi> that is, <hi>objective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> Eccleſiaſtical, deriving from the <hi>King,</hi>) ſo muſt the Authority or Government of the <hi>one</hi> be <hi>cumula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> to, and not <hi>deſtructive</hi> of the <hi>other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is a Notion, which methinks ſhould not be hard of entrance to the <hi>Conformiſt</hi> or <hi>Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt.</hi> On the one ſide the <hi>Biſhop</hi> ſhould receive it, becauſe it grants him his Honour, Dignity, and great Revenues upon a clear and open foundation, and it lightens his care and work. The Office of a <hi>Biſhop</hi> upon this <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> may be diſcharged as that of any other <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> under the King: But the Office of the <hi>Dioceſan</hi> upon the other <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> is a charge he can never perform, and if he live in the negligence of what he thinks his duty, and that wilfully, all his life, how can he be ſaved? On the other ſide, the <hi>Nonconformiſt</hi> ſhould receive it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it opens his Eyes, &amp; lets him ſee how he may be ſubject to the Biſhop, as he is to the <hi>King</hi> and the other <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> under him, without moleſtation to his Conſcience. And this ſhould be the Stone which I would lay for the Foundation (if ever a Parliament would build upon it) of a ſound and laſting Peace in the Nation. Whither this tends, let the Reader ſee farther in the twelfth Section of that univerſally Learned ſort of Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans late Book call'd <hi>The Samaritan.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:65066:19"/>
            <head>An Advertiſement from the Bookſeller.</head>
            <p>THere is a late new Book, Intituled, <hi>A Private Pſalter,</hi> compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the ſame <hi>Hand</hi> that wrote theſe ſheets, which being a <hi>Devotional</hi> Book, is put in a fair Character for the ſake of aged Eyes, and ſold by me, whom the Reader may find out by the Title page.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Parkhurſt.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>An Addition from the Author.</head>
            <p>UPon the mention of this Book I have theſe few words to ſubjoyn concerning the ſame: If I can judg any thing in Divinity, there is hardly any matter of more near importance to the moſt of ſerious Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans than this one thing, to wit, to be ſolidly informed what to do, or how to live, and ſupport the Soul under the caſe when it hath examined itſelf, and is in conflict and doubt whether it be in a <hi>ſtate</hi> of <hi>Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour,</hi> which is all one as whether it be <hi>ſincere</hi> or not. They that are light Chriſtians, do often talk of their aſſurance, when the more weighty Chriſtians are ready to droop and hang the head, as the ears of Corn do that are fulleſt.</p>
            <p>In the laſt Section of the evening Office of that <hi>Private Pſalter,</hi> there is a Determination <hi>de induſtria</hi> of this caſe, according as I was able to admit Inſtruction with Devotion into my Deſign. I am ſenſible of the <hi>ſmallneſs</hi> of my <hi>Talent,</hi> and the <hi>greatneſs</hi> of the <hi>Concern,</hi> and that whatſoever is <hi>peculiar,</hi> is in danger to be <hi>defective,</hi> who muſt confeſs my <hi>genius</hi> hath led me to the ſeeking a <hi>middle</hi> reſolution in this great <hi>Practical</hi> caſe, in regard to <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Comfort,</hi> as it hath uſually done in the matter of polemical <hi>Opinions.</hi> And for the ſake of this caſe more eſpecially was that Book printed.</p>
            <p>If any worthy Perſon therefore of the <hi>Conforming</hi> Miniſtry, who hath a Pen accompliſhed with the ſtile of the Times (whoſe fluency, or command of words may make the task eaſy to him, which would be <hi>bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſome</hi> to me) will take the ſenſe only, or matter of that laſt Section, I mean the full and whole ſenſe of it, though nothing elſe purely but what is there hinted, and enlarge it into a Treatiſe of a convenient dimenſion, as he ſhall pitch upon a ſubject to exerciſe his parts, which I think like to be profitable to moſt Chriſtians, eſpecially to ſuch as are of a tender Spirit, and ſolicitous about their Spiritual eſtate, ſo if he will bring it to the Bookſeller, above intimated, to put it into the Preſs, he will not be ungrateful to him, I ſuppoſe, for his Copy.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Humfrey.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
